Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs; Records apap041
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs Records
1938-1991
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap041
3.46 cubic ft.
These records document the activities and membership of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs (ESFWC) - the umbrella organization of New York State African-American women's groups - from 1938-1991. The collection also includes records from affiliated organizations: the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (NACWC) and the Northeast Federation of Women's Clubs (NFWC).
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Some of the items in this collection were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by the M.C. Lawton Civic and Cultural Club, of Albany, NY, on 17 April 1990. Others were donated on 16 November 1990 by Virginia Poyer, Buenia Brown, and Isabell Harris of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs.
Administrative History
Founded in Brooklyn in 1908 by Alice Wiley Seay, the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs (ESFWC) is the umbrella organization of New York State African-American women's groups.
The women who started the ESFWC had two main goals: to do "uplift work among girls and young women" and to care for the aged Harriet Tubman and her Auburn, Cayuga County home. Narrowly speaking, the latter mission ended with Tubman's death in 1913 and the refusal of the African Methodist Episcopal Zion Church, which owned her property, to lease or sell it to the ESFWC; however, in subsequent years the organization has devoted itself to preserving historic sites associated with African-American leaders such as Frederick Douglass.
The former mission, performing "uplift work among girls and young women," has shaped the group's activities throughout the entirety of its existence. The organization consistently contributed to charitable causes and scholarship funds benefiting African-American girls and young women, and after the Second World War began sponsoring beauty pageants and organizing girls' clubs. The girls' clubs were affiliated with the Empire State Federation of Girls' Clubs, which was established in 1933 and met during the ESFWC's annual conventions. In the 1960's, the ESFWC began assisting in the organizing of boys' clubs, and in late 1987 or early 1988 the Empire State Federation of Girls' Clubs became the Empire State Federation of Youth Clubs.
Throughout its history, the group's efforts to aid African-American girls have been rooted in larger goals: ensuring the physical, intellectual and spiritual well-being of children and adolescents of both sexes and improving the conditions in which African-Americans and people of all races live, learn, and labor. The group has staunchly opposed all forms of racial prejudice and supported the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the National Urban League, and the civil rights movement. During the postwar period, it became interested in the work of Planned Parenthood and the United Nations, and in the 1960's devoted increasing attention to health care issues.
The ESFWC has long been affiliated to the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (NACWC), which was founded in 1896 and rapidly became the largest organization of African-American women in the United States. Heavily influenced by its members' staunch Christian faith and committed to the advancement of African-American women, children, and men and the preservation of African-American history, the NACWC's orientation has closely paralleled that of the ESFWC. In addition to sending funds to the NACWC national offices and delegates to its annual convention, the ESFWC has also been active in the NACWC's regional organization, the Northeastern Federation of Women's Clubs (NFWC), to which it affiliated in 1910.
The ESFWC is headed by a president and an executive board elected at the organization's annual conventions. Seated on the executive board are the board chairman/person, first and second vice-presidents, recording secretary, corresponding secretary, treasurer, financial secretary, parliamentarian, auditor, chaplain, the presidents of each of the ESFWC's regional subdivisions, and the presidents of all of the ESFWC's constituent clubs. Until the late 1970's, the board met once immediately before or during the organization's July annual convention and once during the early autumn or early winter. After that time, the board began meeting immediately before and after the annual convention in July and during each quarter of the year. Special committees charged with planning the convention, investigating various issues, and performing other work are appointed by the president.
Scope and Contents
These records document the activities and membership of the Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs (ESFWC) from 1939-1991. Materials in the collection include meeting minutes, annual convention programs and ephemera, account books, correspondence, and materials concerning the ESFWC's constituent organizations, the Northeastern Federation of Women's Clubs (NFWC) and the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (NACWC). Records span from 1938-1991, but the bulk of them were generated in 1939-44, 1946-64, and 1968-1991.
The Executive Board and Annual Convention Minutes document in detail the membership levels and financial status of the organization and its political, charitable, and social activities. Some highlights include discussion of letters sent to presidents Franklin Delano Roosevelt and Harry Truman concerning racial discrimination in the armed forces, defense industries and federal housing programs and to the mayor of Albany, Georgia concerning the treatment of civil rights leaders Martin Luther King and Ralph Abernathy. Unfortunately, materials documenting the ESFWC's reaction to and support for the upsurge of African-American activism in the 1960's are scarce; the meeting minutes from 1964-68 are missing, and the surviving documents created in the 1960's and early 1970's typically concern internal administrative affairs.
The minutes do detail the ESFWC's position on a broad array of social issues. The organization has vocally opposed all forms of racial prejudice. It condemned lynching (1943, 1947) and discrimination in the armed forces, defense industries, and federal housing programs (1942-43, 1946), and the punitive attitude of some local officials who disbursed Aid to Families with Dependent Children (1961) benefits. It supported the civil rights struggle that took place in the South during the 1950's and 1960's; however, it apparently had little use for the black-power movement (1973). The ESFWC also took interest in a number of issues that affect women. It discussed the Equal Rights Amendment in 1944 and in the 1970's urged its ratification. It was interested in the work of Planned Parenthood (1947, 1950) and in the issue of abortion (1970; see also ESFWC Annual Convention Materials, 1975). Although its relations with white women's organizations are hard to determine, in 1963 it decided to allow white women to become members.
The minutes also document the ESFWC's interest in education and world peace. It urged the New York State Education Department to include African-American history in school curricula (1964) and evidently opposed the increasing acceptance of "black English" (1973). At least some of its members wanted Governor Hugh Carey to explain why the monies generated by the state lottery were not sufficient to prevent teacher layoffs and school budget cutbacks (see ESFWC Annual Convention Materials, 1975). As of 1938, the organization had a Peace Council and remained keenly interested in averting armed conflict (1962). The organization took an active interest in the United Nations (1950), and members apparently toured United Nations headquarters whenever an ESFWC convention was held in New York City.
Information about the organization's finances is scattered throughout the Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes. However, financial records generated during the 1960's and early 1970's are contained largely in the Subject Files of the Financial Secretary and the Subject Files of the Treasurer. Many of these records were apparently created and compiled by Ruth Hurd Inman, who served as the financial secretary (1962-66) and treasurer (1966-c.1970) during these years. In keeping with the organization's rules, Inman seems to have passed them on to Virginia Poyer, who served as financial secretary (1968-73) and added to them.
Records documenting the ESFWC's links to the NFWC and the NACWC are contained largely within the General Subject Files. However, the Correspondence of the President and the correspondence contained in the Subject Files of the Financial Secretary also shed light upon the relations of the ESFWC to its parent organizations. ESFWC officers sometimes served on the executive boards of the NFWC and the NACWC, and some of the letters they received concerned their work on behalf of these organizations.
Materials documenting the activities of constituent clubs and biographical information about ESFWC members and officers are relatively sparse, but information about some clubs and clubwomen is contained in the Correspondence of the President, the ESFWC Subject Files, the correspondence contained in the Subject Files of the Financial Secretary, the Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes. The 1980 annual convention minutes, which consist largely of manuscript reports of constituent clubs' activities, are especially detailed. The NACWC Per Capita Tax Reports contained within the Subject Files of the Financial Secretary are also of particular interest: they list the name and address of every woman who belonged to the ESFWC between 1961 and 1972.
Some of the older documents in the collection are fragile and should be handled carefully. In a few instances, documents have been photocopied for preservation purposes; pencilled notations appear on all photocopied materials. The records were in some instances clearly out of order and were thus rearranged to facilitate use; however, the original order has been respected whenever possible. The subject files concerning the ESFWC's administrative and social service activities and the work of organizations in which the ESFWC took an active interest are the most extensively reconstructed.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1938-1990
Series 2 - Annual Convention Materials, 1944-1991
Series 3 - Correspondence of President, 1954-1990
Series 4 - Subject Files of Financial Secretary, 1948-1981
Series 5 - Subject Files of Treasurer, 1938-1977
Series 6 - ESFWC Subject Files, 1952-1991
Series 7 - General Subject Files, 1952-1990
Series 1-3 are arranged chronologically. Series 4 is arranged alphabetically. Series 5-7 are arranged alphabetically by subject.
African Americans and Civil Rights Organizations; Women; Ethnic Groups; Associations, institutions, etc.--African American membership--Women--New York (State); Civil rights movements--United States; Social action--United States; New York (State); Correspondence; Minutes; Programs (documents); Financial Records; Empire State Federation of Women's Clubs; Northeastern Federation of Women's Clubs; National Association of Colored Women's Clubs (U.S.)
- Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1938-1990; 1; 0.73 cubic ft.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists chiefly of minutes of the meetings of the ESFWC executive board (1939-1944, 1946-1964, 1968, 1970-1971, 1973-1976, 1979, 1982-1983, 1985-1986, 1988-1989) and annual convention (1939-1944, 1946-1964, 1970-1971, 1973-1976, 1980, 1982, 1983-1990). Between 1939-1944 and 1946-1964, the minutes were recorded in bound ledgers. From 1968 onward, they consist of loose manuscript or typescript materials. Information concerning the financial affairs of the organization is scattered throughout. From 1968 onward, routine correspondence that was discussed at meetings is also included; these materials, which were generated by the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs and other organizations, were inserted into the minutes by ESFWC officers and have thus been kept in place. The minutes detail the ESFWC's position on a broad array of social issues, including lynching (1943, 1947), discrimination in the armed forces, defense industries, and federal housing programs (1942-43, 1946), and the punitive attitude of some local officials who disbursed Aid to Families with Dependent Children benefits (1961). The minutes also document the EFSWC's support for the civil rights struggle that took place in the South during the 1950's and 1960's and its apparent dislike of the black-power movement (1973). In addition, the minutes chronicle the organization's interest in the Equal Rights Amendment (1944; 1970's), the work of Planned Parenthood (1947, 1950), the issue of abortion (1970; see also ESFWC Annual Convention Materials, 1975), and its decision to allow white women to become members (1963). Other topics discussed include education (1964, 1973; see also ESFWC Annual Convention Materials, 1975), peace (1930's, 1962), and the work of the United Nations (1950's).
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1938-1956 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 1)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1957-1964 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 2)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1961-1968 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 3)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1961-1964 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 4)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1968-1971 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 5)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1973 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 6)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 7)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1975 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 8)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 9)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1978-1980 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 10)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1981-1982 (Box 1 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 11)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1983 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 1)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1984 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 2)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1985 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 3)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1986 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 4)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1987-1988 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 5)
  - Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 2 (1-Executive Board and Annual Convention Meeting Minu), Folder 6)
- Annual Convention Materials, 1944-1991; 2; 0.4 cubic ft.
  This series consists of convention programs and souvenir journals (1944, 1955-1956, 1958, 1961, 1965-1966, 1968-1969, 1974, 1977-1978, 1984, 1986-1988, 1990-1991), fliers encouraging clubwomen to attend conventions, drafts of resolutions to be forwarded at conventions, and ephemera. Some of the programs detail meeting agendas and the results of officer elections; most of the souvenir journals consist largely of advertisements taken out by the group's members and supporters. The resolutions, which often concern broad public-policy initiatives, are of particular interest (1975).
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1944 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 1)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1955 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 2)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1956 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 3)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1958 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 4)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1959 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 5)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1961 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 6)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1961 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 7)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1963 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 8)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1964 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 9)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1965 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 10)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1966 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 11)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1968 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 12)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1969 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 13)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1970 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 14)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1971 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 15)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1972 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 16)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1973 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 17)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1974 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 18)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1975 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 19)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1976 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 20)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1977 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 21)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1978 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 22)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1979 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 23)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1980 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 24)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1981 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 25)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1983 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 26)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1984 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 27)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1986 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 28)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1987 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 29)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1988 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 30)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1989 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 31)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1990 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 32)
  - Annual Convention Materials, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Annual Convention Materials), Folder 33)
- Correspondence of President, 1954-1990; 3; 0.17 cubic ft.
  Most of the materials in this series, which includes letters received by and copies of correspondence written by the president, concern routine organizational business. However, some of the letters shed light on the friendships that helped to sustain club women and the pleasures and frustrations of serving as an ESFWC officer.
  - Correspondence of President, 1954-1969 (Box 1 (3-Correspondence of President), Folder 1)
  - Correspondence of President, 1973-1977 (Box 1 (3-Correspondence of President), Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of President, 1978-1981 (Box 1 (3-Correspondence of President), Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of President, 1986-1990 (Box 1 (3-Correspondence of President), Folder 4)
- Subject Files of Financial Secretary, 1948-1981; 4; 1.0 cubic ft.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series consists of records created or maintained by the ESFWC financial secretary. Materials include annual convention forms (1960, 1962, 1964), annual convention registration lists (c.1964-1967) and an executive board meeting registration list (1966) showing fees paid, correspondence (1961, 1962-1967, 1969), and financial records pertaining to the Empire State Association of Girls (1962, 1964-1966). Ledgers (1948-1967) and financial reports (1965-1966, 1969-1972, 1978-1981) detailing receipts and disbursements and forms documenting constituent club members' payment of dues to the National Association of Colored Women's Clubs or, in a few instances, Northeast Federation of Women's Clubs (1961-1971) dominate the series. Other records include financial reports concerning the ESFWC's annual Miss Empire State Contest (1962, 1969) and member contributions to Negro Braille magazine (c. 1969) and to the Victoria Earle Matthews Scholarship Fund for African-American girls (c. 1969, 1972).
  - Annual Convention Credential Forms, 1960 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 2)
  - Annual Convention Credential Forms, 1962 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 2)
  - Annual Convention Credential Forms, 1964 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 3)
  - Annual Convention Registration, 1965-1967 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 5)
  - Bank Statements and Banking Documents, ca. 1965-1985 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 6)
  - Budgets and Reports of Budget Commitee, 1971-ca. 1980 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 7)
  - Club Woman of the Year Contest, 1970 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1963 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 16)
  - Empire State Association of Girls' Clubs Reports and NACWC Per Capita Tax Reports, 1964-1966 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 17)
  - Executive Board Meeting Registration, 1966-ca. 1970 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 18)
  - Financial Reports, 1965-1981 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 19)
  - Ledger, 1948-1962 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 20)
  - Ledger, 1963-1965 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 21)
  - Ledger, 1963-1966 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 22)
  - Ledger, 1964-1967 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 23)
  - Mink Stole Committee Report, 1972 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 24)
  - Miss Empire State Contest, 1962-1969 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 25)
  - NACWC Per Capita Tax Reports, 1961-1962 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 26)
  - NACWC Per Capita Tax Reports, 1963 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 27)
  - NACWC Per Capita Tax Reports, 1964 (Box 1 (4-Subject Files of Financial Secretary), Folder 28)